<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- 
For use when a committee document points at the OASIS web site for publishing:
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" 
href="http://docs.oasis-open.org/templates/DocBook/spec-0.6/stylesheets/oasis-specification-html.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" 

For use when a committee document points to an embedded runtime installation:
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" 
         href="htmlruntime/spec-0.6/stylesheets/oasis-specification-html.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" 
        "htmlruntime/spec-0.6/docbook/docbookx.dtd" 

For use when a committee document is published in a local environment only
(note the instructions for local publishing require adjusting the stylesheet
 and DocBook directories in these declarations):
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" 
href="file:///c:/oasis/spec-0.6/stylesheets/oasis-specification-html-offline.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
         "file:///c:/oasis/spec-0.6/docbook/docbookx.dtd" 
-->
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../htmlruntime/spec-0.6/stylesheets/oasis-specification-html-offline.xsl"?>
<!--
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../../htmlruntime/spec-0.6/stylesheets/oasis-specification-fo-us.xsl"?>
-->
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" 
[
<!ENTITY name "xdi-signatures">
<!ENTITY pversion "0.0">
<!ENTITY version "1.0">
<!ENTITY stage "wd01">
<!ENTITY standard "Working Draft 01">
<!ENTITY this-loc "http://docs.oasis-open.org/templates/DocBook/spec-&version;">
<!ENTITY previous-loc "http://docs.oasis-open.org/templates/DocBook/spec-&pversion;">
<!ENTITY latest-loc "http://docs.oasis-open.org/templates/DocBook/oasis-specification">
<!ENTITY pubdate "23 May 2014">
<!ENTITY title "XDI Signatures V&version;">
<!ENTITY % xinclude SYSTEM "/Applications/oxygen-13.2/frameworks/docbook/4.4/dtd/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
]>
<article status="&standard;">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>&title;</title>
    <releaseinfo role="cvs"> $Id: oasis-specification-0.6-wd04.xml,v 1.2 2012/06/14 01:57:23 admin
      Exp $ </releaseinfo>
    <productname>&name;</productname>
    <productnumber>&version;-&stage;</productnumber>
    <releaseinfo role="track">Standards Track Work Product</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-this-authoritative"
      >&this-loc;/&name;-&version;-&stage;.html</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-this"
      >&this-loc;/&name;-&version;-&stage;.pdf</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-this"
      >&this-loc;/&name;-&version;-&stage;.xml</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-previous-authoritative"
      >&previous-loc;/&name;-&pversion;.html</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-previous"
      >&previous-loc;/&name;-&pversion;.pdf</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-previous"
      >&previous-loc;/&name;-&pversion;.xml</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-latest-authoritative"
      >&latest-loc;/&name;.html</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-latest">&latest-loc;/&name;.pdf</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="OASIS-specification-latest">&latest-loc;/&name;.xml</releaseinfo>
    <releaseinfo role="committee"><ulink url="https://www.oasis-open.org/apps/org/workgroup/xdi/"
        >OASIS XRI Data Interchange (XDI) TC</ulink></releaseinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <editor>
        <firstname>Peter</firstname>
        <surname>Davis</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>Neustar, Inc.</orgname>
        </affiliation>
        <email>peter.davis@neustar.biz</email>
      </editor>
      <editor>
        <firstname>Dan</firstname>
        <surname>Blum</surname>
        <affiliation>
          <orgname>Respect Network Corp.</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </editor>
    </authorgroup>
    <pubdate>&pubdate;</pubdate>
    <copyright>
      <year>2014</year>
      <holder>OASIS Open, Inc. All Rights Reserved.</holder>
    </copyright>
    <legalnotice role="additional">
      <title>Additional artifacts</title>
      <para>This &standard; is part of a broader suite of specifications collectively referred to as
        XDI &version;. The following specifications constitute the complete suite: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Core <xref linkend="XDICore"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Messaging <xref linkend="XDIMsg"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Discovery <xref linkend="XDIDisco"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Policy <xref linkend="XDIPolicy"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Security Mechanisms <xref linkend="XDISec"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Privacy <xref linkend="XDIPriv"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Dictionary <xref linkend="XDIDictionary"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Signature <xref linkend="XDISig"/></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </legalnotice>
    <abstract>
      <title>Abstract</title>
      <para>This &standard; specifies methods to create and validate cryptographic signatures for
          <glossterm linkend="g.xdi">XDI</glossterm> statements, subgraphs and protocol
        messages.</para>
    </abstract>
    <legalnotice role="notices">
      <title>Notices</title>
      <para>Copyright &#169; OASIS&#174; Open 2012. All Rights Reserved. </para>
      <para>All capitalized terms in the following text have the meanings assigned to them in the
        OASIS Intellectual Property Rights Policy (the "OASIS IPR Policy"). The full Policy may be
        found at <ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/who/intellectualproperty.php"
          >http://www.oasis-open.org/who/intellectualproperty.php</ulink>.</para>
      <para>This document and translations of it may be copied and furnished to others, and
        derivative works that comment on or otherwise explain it or assist in its implementation may
        be prepared, copied, published, and distributed, in whole or in part, without restriction of
        any kind, provided that the above copyright notice and this section are included on all such
        copies and derivative works. However, this document itself may not be modified in any way,
        including by removing the copyright notice or references to OASIS, except as needed for the
        purpose of developing any document or deliverable produced by an OASIS Technical Committee
        (in which case the rules applicable to copyrights, as set forth in the OASIS IPR Policy,
        must be followed) or as required to translate it into languages other than English.</para>
      <para>The limited permissions granted above are perpetual and will not be revoked by OASIS or
        its successors or assigns.</para>
      <para>This document and the information contained herein is provided on an "AS IS" basis and
        OASIS DISCLAIMS ALL WARRANTIES, EXPRESS OR IMPLIED, INCLUDING BUT NOT LIMITED TO ANY
        WARRANTY THAT THE USE OF THE INFORMATION HEREIN WILL NOT INFRINGE ANY OWNERSHIP RIGHTS OR
        ANY IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY OR FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</para>
      <para>OASIS requests that any OASIS Party or any other party that believes it has patent
        claims that would necessarily be infringed by implementations of this OASIS Committee
        Specification or OASIS Standard, to notify OASIS TC Administrator and provide an indication
        of its willingness to grant patent licenses to such patent claims in a manner consistent
        with the IPR Mode of the OASIS Technical Committee that produced this specification.</para>
      <para>OASIS invites any party to contact the OASIS TC Administrator if it is aware of a claim
        of ownership of any patent claims that would necessarily be infringed by implementations of
        this specification by a patent holder that is not willing to provide a license to such
        patent claims in a manner consistent with the IPR Mode of the OASIS Technical Committee that
        produced this specification. OASIS may include such claims on its website, but disclaims any
        obligation to do so.</para>
      <para>OASIS takes no position regarding the validity or scope of any intellectual property or
        other rights that might be claimed to pertain to the implementation or use of the technology
        described in this document or the extent to which any license under such rights might or
        might not be available; neither does it represent that it has made any effort to identify
        any such rights. Information on OASIS' procedures with respect to rights in any document or
        deliverable produced by an OASIS Technical Committee can be found on the OASIS website.
        Copies of claims of rights made available for publication and any assurances of licenses to
        be made available, or the result of an attempt made to obtain a general license or
        permission for the use of such proprietary rights by implementers or users of this OASIS
        Committee Specification or OASIS Standard, can be obtained from the OASIS TC Administrator.
        OASIS makes no representation that any information or list of intellectual property rights
        will at any time be complete, or that any claims in such list are, in fact, Essential
        Claims.</para>
      <para>The name "OASIS" is a trademark of <ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org">OASIS</ulink>,
        the owner and developer of this specification, and should be used only to refer to the
        organization and its official outputs. OASIS welcomes reference to, and implementation and
        use of, specifications, while reserving the right to enforce its marks against misleading
        uses. Please see <ulink url="http://www.oasis-open.org/who/trademark.php"
          >http://www.oasis-open.org/who/trademark.php</ulink> for above guidance.</para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>
  <section id="s.intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>Signatures for XDI can be applied to individual statements (triples), subgraphs and XDI
      protocol messages. XDI Security Mechanisms <xref linkend="XDISec"/> requires that XDI messages
      should incorporate methods to authenticate message originators, as well as methods to ensure
      message integrity. XDI Signatures provides one such method. </para>
    <section>
      <title>Related Publications</title>
      <para>This &standard; is part of a broader suite of specifications collectively referred to as
        XDI &version;. The following specifications constitute the complete suite: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Core <xref linkend="XDICore"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Messaging <xref linkend="XDIMsg"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Discovery <xref linkend="XDIDisco"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Policy <xref linkend="XDIPolicy"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Security Mechanisms <xref linkend="XDISec"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Privacy <xref linkend="XDIPriv"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Dictionary <xref linkend="XDIDictionary"/></para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>XDI Signature <xref linkend="XDISig"/></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Terminology and Notation Conventions</title>
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../xdi-docbook-util/rfc2119.xml"/>
      <!-- import normative lang -->
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        href="../xdi-docbook-util/xdi-glossary-wd01.xml"/>
      <!-- import notation -->
      <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../xdi-docbook-util/notation.xml"/>
      <!-- import normative lang -->
    </section>
    <section id="s.design">
      <title>Design Requirements</title>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Requirements for signatures:</emphasis>
        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>A graph must be able to describe specific charateristics of cryptograph material
              netadata.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A graph subject must be able to sign specific subgraphs. (e.g.
                <code>(=example/#friend)</code>).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A graph subject signs a specific triple found in her graph (e.g.
                <code>=example&lt;#email>&amp;/&amp;/"me@example.com"</code>).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>A third party creates a signature over a subgraph (or single triple) to place in
              another entities graph (e.g.
                <code>=example&lt;#email>&lt;#work>&amp;/&amp;/"person@example.org"</code> signed by
                <code>@example</code>).</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Determine what is (and is not) signed in a specific graph by direct analysis of
              the signature triple.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Ability to validate a signature made by the graph subject or a third party</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
        <emphasis role="bold">Requirements for encryption: </emphasis><orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>it must be possible to encrypt literals in the graph</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>it must be possible to encrypt a single statement in the graph</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>it must be possible to encrypt sub graphs in the graph</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>methods must be provided to address statements and sub graphs that are
              encrypted</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>it must be possible to signal when encrypted data must be stored in its' encrypted
              form (or not)</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="s.usage">
    <title>Usage</title>
    <para><xref linkend="XDISec"/> recommends that XDI messages should incorporate mechanisms for
      confidentiality, integrity and authenticity. This specification defines the manner in which
      cryptograph material, including certain metadata, can be included in a graph. It also defines
      methods for establishing signatures for XDI messages, the syntax for expressing these
      signatures as a sequence of triples suitable for storage in a graph. Lastly, it specifies
      methods for encrypting literals, triples, subgraphs and whole messages.</para>
    <para>Since both encryption and signatures require cryptographic key material (semetric or
      asymetric), certain characteristics of the key material must be described. This metadata is
      defined in <xref linkend="s.keymeta"/>.</para>
    <para>XDI Signatures consist of several characteristics: Algorythm information, Hashing
      information, and The signature itself. Processing instructions for the creation and validation
      of XDI signatures are provided in section <xref linkend="s.sigproccess"/>. </para>
    <para>There are several applications for XDI signatures. For XDI messages, they may be used to
      fufill the requirements in <xref linkend="XDISec"/> for message integrity and authenticity.
      For graph representations, signatures can indicate that the signer is asserting specific
      statements in the graph (for example, the graph subject is asserting a list of friends
      addressed by the inner root (<code>=example/#friend</code>) ). Signatures can also be placed
      in a third parties graph, indicating that the signer is asserting one or more statements about
      the graph subject (e.g. a subject's emlployer asserts the work email address of the
      subject).</para>
    <para>The encryption mechanisms defined in this document are ssufficient to fullfill the
      confidentiality requirements defined in <xref linkend="XDISec"/>. The mecahnics of encrypting
      information in the graph, as well as the neccesary encryption metadata are defined in <xref
        linkend="s.encprocess"/></para>
    <para><xref linkend="schema"/></para>
  </section>
  <section id="s.cryptmeta">
    <title>Cryptography Metadata</title>
    <para>Performing cryptographic operations on graphs, subgraphs and messages requires message
      recipients to posses select information about the algorythms and keys in order to reverse or
      reproduce the operations. The metadata defined in this section is also incorporated in <xref
        linkend="XDIDictionary"/> for reference.</para>
    <section id="s.keymeta">
      <title>Key Metadata</title>
      <para>Key material expressed in a graph require descirptive charateristics of the key for
        proper application of cryptographic operations. The following dictionary terms are used to
        describe symetric and asymetric keys.</para>
      <xi:include href="../xdi-dictionary-1.0/xdi-dictionary-1.0-wd01.xml" xpointer="d.key"/>
      <xi:include href="../xdi-dictionary-1.0/xdi-dictionary-1.0-wd01.xml" xpointer="d.x509"/>
      <xi:include href="../xdi-dictionary-1.0/xdi-dictionary-1.0-wd01.xml" xpointer="d.keyencode"/>
    </section>
    <section id="s.sigmeta">
      <title>Signature Metadata</title>
      <para>To construct the <glossterm>Signature Block</glossterm>, the following statements MUST
        be added to the <glossterm>Normalized Graph</glossterm>: </para>
      <section>
        <title>Signature Algorithm</title>
        <para>The Algorithm <glossterm>Signature Block</glossterm> statement identifies the
          cryptographic algorithm used to secure the signature.</para>
        <example id="e.alg">
          <title>Signature Algorithm Example</title>
          <programlisting/>
          <para/>
        </example>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Canonicalization Method</title>
        <para/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Digest Method</title>
        <para/>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="s.encmeta">
      <title>Encryption Metadata</title>
      <xi:include href="../xdi-dictionary-1.0/xdi-dictionary-1.0-wd01.xml" xpointer="d.encrypted"/>
      <para/>
      <xi:include href="../xdi-dictionary-1.0/xdi-dictionary-1.0-wd01.xml" xpointer="d.mime"/>
      <section>
        <title>MimeType</title>
        <para/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>Encoding</title>
        <para/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>EncyptionMethod</title>
        <para/>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>CypherText</title>
        <para/>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="s.sigproccess">
    <title>XDI Signatures</title>
    <para>Notes:</para>
    <para>signatures that require SHA-256 <xref linkend="SHA"/> or greater hashing, and allows for
      HMAC <xref linkend="RFC2104"/>, RSA <xref linkend="RFC3447"/> and ECDSA <xref linkend="TBD"/>
      algorithms. In the future, additional hashing and encryption algorithms may be added.</para>
    <para>Signatures over sub-graphs are established in a manner such that the signature may be
      included in the graph. This includes signatures over XDI Messages defined in <xref
        linkend="XDIMsg"/>. The signature covers the entire XDI subgraph rooted in that context node
      at that point in time. Signature may be made with a signing key rooted in the same graph as
      the graph from which the signature and signed content was obtained, or the signing key may be
      located in a different graph altogether.</para>
    <para>Recipients of signed XDI messages SHOULD validate all signatures present in the
      response.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Signature Processing Rules</title>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Canonical Representation</title>
      <para>Signing XDI statements and messages involves first normalizing to the XDI Flat
        Serialization as defined in <xref linkend="XDICore"/>, and afterwards, incorporation of a
          <glossterm>Signature Block</glossterm> in a manner not disruptive to validators.</para>
      <para>XDI Flat Serialization is the only serialization format used for signature creation and
        validation. Implementations that choose to transfer XDI messages in another serialization
        format MUST serialize the message in XDI Flat Serialization prior to attempting
        validation.</para>
      <section>
        <title>Canonicalization Process</title>
        <para>The following steps MUST be performed in this order to produce the
            <glossterm>Normalized Graph</glossterm>. These requirements apply to message senders as
          well as message recipients.</para>
        <para>
          <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
            <listitem>
              <para>Ensure the sub-graph is UTF-8 encoded and formatted as defined in XDI Flat
                Serialization defined in <xref linkend="XDICore"/>.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>All unquoted white space and new lines MUST be removed (TODO: better clarify
                white space. should this go into XdiFlatSerialization?)</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>All JSON <xref linkend="RFC4627"/> keys in the unsigned graph MUST be sorted in
                UTF-8 <xref linkend="RFC3629"/> byte-order.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="s.alg">
      <title>Algorithms</title>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Graph Signatures</title>
      <para/>
      <section>
        <title>Link Contract Considerations for Signatures</title>
        <para>Signature authors, may need to establish a specific <glossterm>Link
            Contract</glossterm> associated with the signature, especially when the signature is
          placed in a remote graph from the signed <glossterm>XDI subgraph</glossterm> or
            <glossterm>XDI Statement</glossterm>. Signatures need not be publicly available, but
          SHOULD be made available to anticipated relying parties.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Message Signatures</title>
      <para/>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="s.encprocess">
    <title>Encryption Processing Rules</title>
    <para>TODO: encrypt literals, encrypt single statement, encrypt sub graph. how to address hidden
      statements</para>
  </section>
  <section id="s.seccon">
    <title>Security Considerations</title>
    <para/>
  </section>
  <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    href="../xdi-docbook-util/xdi-biblio-wd01.xml"/>
  <!-- import biblio -->
  <appendix id="s.examples">
    <title>Examples</title>
    <section>
      <title>Graph Signature Examples</title>
      <para/>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Message Signature Examples</title>
      <para/>
    </section>
  </appendix>
  <appendix id="s.revhist">
    <title>Revision History</title>
    <para>
      <revhistory>
        <revision>
          <revnumber>wd1</revnumber>
          <date>23 May 2014</date>
          <authorinitials>pcd</authorinitials>
          <revremark>Initial draft incorporating general outline, and initial proposed signing
            processing rules.</revremark>
        </revision>
        <revision>
          <revnumber>wd1</revnumber>
          <date>29 May</date>
          <authorinitials>pcd</authorinitials>
          <revremark>Reorganization to allow the document to describe gerneralized cryptographic
            operations. Added distinct metadata sections for keys, signatures and
            encryption.</revremark>
        </revision>
      </revhistory>
    </para>
  </appendix>
</article>
